A Guide to the Papers of Carter Glass 1858-1946, and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence 1922-1927 (Box 240)
  A. Folder on the McFadden Bill in 1927: Typed statement made by Carter Glass giving his ideas of the merits of the bill and the procedure necessary to get it passed and his view of the Hull amendments; Letter from Louis T. McFadden to members of the House regarding proposed changes in his bill, 1927; Letter from the Senate conferees to Louis T. McFadden; Booklet on, "Facts versus Misstatements regarding the McFadden Bill;" Letters from constituents expressing opinions on the bill.
  B. Folder of letters making arrangements for Carter Glass to make a speech in Greenville, South Carolina, 1924.
  C. About 400-500 letters from constituents expressing their opinions on the soldiers bonus bill, 1922.
- Correspondence 1934, 1940 (Box 241)
  A. Folder of correspondence and editorials endorsing Carter Glass for the Democratic presidential nomination, 1934; Folder of ca. 350 letters congratulating Carter Glass on a speech made in 1940 at the Democratic National Convention in which he denounced a third term for Franklin D. Roosevelt and nominated James A. Farley.
- Correspondence 1922-1924 (Box 242)
  A. Requests for Carter Glass to speak to various groups or to attend various performances, ceremonies, shows, etc., 1922-1924.
- Correspondence 1923 (Box 243)
  A. Invitations for Carter Glass to attend various ceremonies and gatherings, or for him to speak to certain groups, 1923.
- Correspondence Legislation 1924-1920 (Box 244)
  A. Folder of political correspondence with J. T. Deal of the second district of Virginia, 1923-1930; Folder of correspondence with Senator Capper dealing almost entirely with legislation regarding public utilities in the District of Columbia; Correspondence with G. O'Connor Goolrick, for the most part over a state Democratic primary in which Harry F. Byrd and Mapp were candidates; Personal and political correspondence with Vance C. McCormick regarding opinions on national political matters, monetary matters, etc.; Correspondence with Colonel James P. Woods, dealing mostly with state politics in Virginia; Folder of miscellaneous political and legislative correspondence with Congressman R. Walton Moore; Folder of correspondence with Colonel W. S. Battle of Roanoke, Virginia dealing with the Virginia political situation and to some extent with Bishop James Cannon and his controversy with Carter Glass.
- Correspondence 1923-1929 (Box 245)
  A. Letters congratulating Carter Glass on a statement made by him rebuking seven democrats who issued some sort of point statement after their election in 1930; Letters congratulating Carter Glass on his re- election in 1924; Letters acknowledging receipt of an autographed copy of Carter Glass' book by his friends; Letters expressing opinions on his book, " An Adventure in Constructive Finance; " Requests for copies of a speech by Carter Glass attacking critics of the Federal Reserve System, 1923; Letters acknowledging a cartoon sent to his friends by Carter Glass as a Thanksgiving gift in 1929; Letters acknowledging receipt by Carter Glass' friends of a brochure written by him called A Tale of Two Heifers in which he evidently attacked the state legislation authorizing the testing of cows for tuberculosis; Correspondence from the Lynchburg Industrial Savings and Loan Corporation regarding a note which Carter Glass endorsed for a Mrs. Rebecca Spurlock. The bank was threatening to take action because Mrs. Spurlock was in arrears in her payments.
- Correspondence 1941 (Box 246)
  A. Miscellaneous letters concerning legislative matters in 1941: Letters to Carter Glass expressing concern over Morgan Shaw's idea of taxing corporate earnings above a 6% return on capital 100%; Letters from Senator Harry F. Byrd suggesting certain men for appointments, etc.; Letters regarding an attempt to take part of Arlington County, Virginia into the District of Columbia, so that Arlington Cemetery, its airport, Fort Meyer, etc. would be in D. C.; Letters and literature on the results of testing for tuberculosis in cows and the worth of such testing; Bill from Carter Glass' lawyers for presenting his case against the state veterinarian, et al.; Copies of letters received during the Smith campaign, both congratulating and not.
- Correspondence 1925-1926 (Box 247)
  A. Folder of ca. 75-100 letters urging Carter Glass to vote for United States entrance into the World Court, 1925-1926; Ca. 25 letters urging Carter Glass to vote for a pension bill before Congress which would help dependents of service men (1926); Ca. 75 letters, mostly from local lodges of railway brotherhoods, requesting Carter Glass to vote for the Couzens Resolution having to do with the consolidation of railroads; Folder of newspaper clippings regarding an attack by Carter Glass on action by President Coolidge of sanctioning or vetoing private bank loans to foreign governments; Folder of letters from various interests asking for Carter Glass' influence in getting Congress to appropriate money for a cause,1929; Letters to Carter Glass regarding amendment of the Voshead Act and repeal of prohibition, 1926; Folder of newspaper clippings dealing with prohibition, Bishop James Cannon, debt of foreign governments to the United States, political articles about Carter Glass, etc.
- Correspondence Legislation 1925-1930 (Box 248)
  A. Correspondence on proposed legislation regarding Immigration, Reorganization, the Radio bill, Big Navy Bill, McFadden Bill, including letter from Federal Reserve Agent in St. Louis, and Tax Bill, 69th Congress.
- Correspondence Personal and Legislative 1926-1930 (Box 249)
  A. Election contest of William B. Wilson: Letters and papers.
  B. File on Paul M. Warburg: Statement of American Bankers Association favoring indeterminate charters for Federal Reserve banks; two statements by Paul M. Warburg on monetary matters; letters between Carter Glass and Paul M. Warburg relating to passage of McFadden Bill.
  C. File on Dallas Federal Reserve Bank Case; File on Charles Mitchell; Letters from Charles Collins, Assistant Comptroller of the Currency, including some pertaining to McFadden Bill; Folder of correspondence with A. D. Noyes of the New York Times, concerning Houden Smith articles, Paul M. Warburg's influence on Federal Reserve Act, Senator Tom Heflin, and other related matters; Folder of correspondence with Albert Shaw, including letters expressing Carter Glass' view on Federal Reserve Policy in 1928.
- Correspondence Political and Legislative 1920-1930 (Box 250)
  A. Files of correspondence with Harry F. Byrd, concerning the political situation in Virginia in 1927-1928, and the Presidential Campaign of 1928. About 500 letters; Edwin Halsey, regarding the Democratic National Campaign of 1928; Senator Carter Glass and Rixey Smith, including an article by Carter Glass, "The Battle for the Banking Bill," 1927, and concerning primarily routine matters; Benjamin Strong, Governor of Federal Reserve Board of New York including letters on Federal Reserve policies in the 1920's, branch banking, and H. Parker Willis; Norman H. Davis, including letters relating to House and Seymour.
- Hearings 1928 (Box 251)
  A. Senatorial Campaign Expenditures
- Legislative and Personal Correspondence 1927-1936 (Box 252)
  A. Correspondence with George. A. Norris, Governor of the Reserve Board of Philadelphia on Senate Bill 4412 amending the Federal Reserve Act, on the relation between the Federal Reserve Board and Reserve Banks, and on uniformity in discount rates, Ca. 30 letters; Letter from Carter Glass to Robert J. Buckley denying similarity between Aldrich Bill and Federal Reserve Act. Letter from Carter Glass to Frederick A. Delano defining the importance of the position of Comptroller of the Currency; Memorandum regarding consideration of reappointment of Governor Harding; Copy of regulation of Board dealing with par collections and correspondence on this subject; Letters to Robert Carter Glass; Letter from Carter Glass to Edna E. Gaines discussing origin of Federal Reserve Act; Correspondence with Lloyd R. Freeman on call loan rates; Early draft of Federal Reserve Act, May, 1913; Letter to George Donnella, discussing Samuel Untermeyer; Correspondence with John M. Miller, Jr. concerning Glass-Steagall Act; Correspondence with John D. Mershon on origin of Federal Reserve Act; Letter from Edmund Platt and copy of minority report of Board on branch banking, 1923.
- Correspondence: Political Campaign 1928 (Box 253)
  A. Folder of invitations to speak during Presidential Campaign; Letters touching the Presidential Campaign, the Democratic National Platform, and Prohibition.
- Correspondence (Box 254)
  Regarding Tubercular Infection of Animals. Requests from constituents for copies of Senate Docket No. 85.
- Correspondence regarding Tariff 1929-1930 (Box 255)
  A. Ca. 1,500 letters from constituents in regard to their views on proposed tariff legislation.
- Political Correspondence 1928-1930 (Box 256)
  A. Ca. 100 letters acknowledging Carter Glass' form letter of October 20, 1930, asking for support in his re-election campaign; Ca. 500 letters of commendation regarding Carter Glass' radio speech campaign of 1928.
- Political Correspondence 1920-1930 (Box 257)
  A. Folders of correspondence regarding Spotsylvania Battlefield Park; Hon. Joseph P. Tumulty; W. E. Borali; James F. Byrnes; Rixey Smith, 1926 including letters relating to the preparation and publication of " An Adventure in Creative Finance"; Letters to Arthur W. Page concerning publication of Carter Glass' book; Louis Wiley; Col. Henry Anderson; Frank Cabb, Jr.; Walter E. Addison; St. George Tucker.
- Legislative and Personal Correspondence 1929-1935 (Box 258)
  A. Folder of correspondence between Carter Glass and Rixey Smith; Rixey Smith's personal file; Letters, telegrams and newspaper clippings pertaining to the Morgan case, ca. 250; File of correspondence with E. C. Folkes, about 100 letters, dealing primarily with the American bank in Richmond, the use of convicts in road forces, and his desire to obtain a Federal appointment.
- Telegrams regarding Carter Glass Banking Bill 1933 (Box 259)
  A. Ca. 1,500 telegrams from bankers and others throughout the United States endorsing the Carter Glass Banking Bill.
- Correspondence regarding Cannon Case 1930-1931 (Box 260)
  A. Miscellaneous correspondence and documents pertaining to investigation and trial of Bishop James Cannon; 2 letters from Jouett Shouse conveying information on Cannon's activities; Ca. 8 mimeographed copies of statement by Forrest J. Prettyman on manner in which Bishop James Cannon Church trial was conducted; Folder of material concerning Cannon's stock gambling. Copy of Goldhurst's confession; File on Goldhurst parole.
- Correspondence regarding Cannon Case, (S-Z) 1930-1931 (Box 261)
  A. Letters of Charles H. Tuttle, Frank Morgan and Robert Thomas.
  B. Folder of newspaper clippings on Carter Glass' speech November 1, 1932; Statements of Senator Carter Glass on his 1935 banking legislation. Speeches by Carter Glass on various subjects, 1930-1934, including Veterans' Bonus, Farm Relief, Illegal Foreign Loans, and Kellog Peace Pact. Statement of Senator Carter Glass regarding efforts of Federal Reserve Board to curb speculation. Letters of Carter Glass to Bishop James Cannon and Cannon to Carter Glass. Correspondence between Cannon and Cable & Company.
  C. Letter from Carter Glass to Byerly discussing bill for change of reserve on time deposits.
  D. Correspondence with Senator Nye regarding investigation of James Cannon.
- Correspondence regarding Bishop James Cannon Case, (A-D) 1930-1931 (Box 262)
  A. Correspondence pertaining to various aspects of the Bishop James Cannon Case: Ca.1000 pieces including: Ned Daniel, J. Lee Davis, Guston T. Fitzhugh, J. B. Woods, Collins Denny, Ernest Cherrington and others; Letters indicate the important role played by Carter Glass in uncovering evidence against Cannon.
  B. Folder of about 20 letters between Carter Glass and James Cannon.
- Correspondence, Cannon Case, (E-R) 1930-1931 (Box 263)
  A. Miscellaneous correspondence on various aspects of the investigation of James Cannon's activities; Letters verifying Carter Glass' importance as an instigator of the proceedings against Cannon; Correspondence with Daniel Roter, Judge Adolphus Nagan, James O'Brien, Dr. F. J. Prettyman, Charles B. Parkhill, William D. Mitchell, Basil Manley, Rev. J. C. Harrel, W. M. Cravatt, Clara Goldhurst, Guston Fitzhugh, Bishop William N. Ainsworth, and statements of Mrs. Helen McCallum (Cannon) and Mrs. Joan Chapman.
- Correspondence, Bishop James Cannon's Case 1928-1933 (Box 264)
  A. Correspondence with James O'Brien and Judge Adolphus Nagan; Folder of newspaper clippings about Cannon and about Carter Glass' proposed tax on stock market transactions. Photostatic copies of correspondence of J. Edgar Hoover (regarding Goldhurst) and of other papers pertaining to Goldhurst's trial; Folder of correspondence with Harold P. Nye and G. T. Fitzhugh.
- Newspaper Clippings 1930-1931 (Box 265)
  A. Editorials and news accounts of Cannon's stock market transactions.
- Correspondence: Legislative and Political 1929-1932 (Box 266)
  A. Folders of correspondence pertaining to the Banking and Currency meeting, January 19, 1931. Banking Legislation memoranda; letters from bankers offering their appraisals of the existing situation and suggesting improvements; Henry P. Epes, Charles W. Collins, Claude Weaver, and Hon. J. W. Pole, including letters pertaining to the insurance of bank deposits and the branch banking bill.
- Correspondence: Legislation 1930-1935 (Box 267)
  A. Correspondence includes: Letters relating to Stock Exchange Inquiry; Letters and telegrams pertaining to the Woodrow Wilson Foundation. Also financial reports; Correspondence with the Treasury Department, primarily concerning appointments; Letter from Hon. A. H. Vandenburg suggesting an amendment to the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation law; Correspondence with Jouett Shouse on party matters, views of constituents and other subjects; Correspondence between Carter Glass and C. Bascom Slemp; Correspondence with Peter Saunders.
- Correspondence: Political 1930-1935 (Box 268)
  A. Folder of correspondence pertaining to the pamphlet, "You Can Defend America;" Congratulatory letters on 1942 election; Correspondence with Franklin D. Roosevelt, primarily concerning routine political and legislative matters. Some letters of a personal nature; Folder of miscellaneous correspondence and newspaper clippings, including Robert's nomination to Federal Judgeship. Shakespeare controversy, several clippings and an article, "Vapor vs. the Record," concerning Samuel Untermeyer's participation in Federal Reserve legislation; Copy of speech made by him at Richmond, and statements concerning the activities of Bishop James Cannon.
- Correspondence: Legislation 1930-1935 (Box 269)
  A. Folders of letters pertaining to highway construction in Virginia; Correspondence with John J. Raskob regarding his appearance before the banking committee, 1933; Personal correspondence with Dr. L. S. Rowe; Letters relating to the Reconstruction Finance Company; Correspondence with A. L. Ailworth, mostly of a personal or local political nature, 1920-1933.
- Correspondence: Legislation 1928-1933 (Box 270)
  A. Folder of about 600 letters from constituents expressing their views on the World Court, the Disarmament Conference, and Muscle Shoals; Folder of about 300 letters concerning the tariff bill of 1930.
- Correspondence: Personal and Legislative 1930-1935 (Box 271)
  A. Papers pertaining to the Farm Credit Administration; Letters of J. F. T. O'Connor, Comptroller, 1933; Correspondence with George W. Norris concerning policies of the Federal Reserve System; Letters concerning the Joint Stock Land Banks; Letters congratulating Carter Glass on his opposition to the Bonus Bill, 1934; Folder of telegrams concerning banking schemes; General correspondence on appropriations, 1933; Correspondence on agricultural matters, 1933.
- Political Correspondence 1932-1933 (Box 272)
  A. Letters, telegrams and petitions concerning the prohibition issue, ca. 500 pieces, dated 1932-1933; Correspondence with George L. Harris, Governor of Federal Reserve Bank of New York, on Federal Reserve policies and monetary and banking practices and legislation, including statement of Board of New York Bank regarding Banking Legislation, 1932.
- Political Correspondence 1930-1935 (Box 273)
  A. Two folders of correspondence between Carter Glass and Rixey Smith on various aspects of the Cannon investigation; Folder of miscellaneous correspondence, including letters of Jesse H. Jones, Harold L. Ickes, Louis T. McFadden and William McAdoo; Folder of letters and clippings relating to the Morgan investigation; Folder of miscellaneous papers including a speech on the Federal Reserve Act, delivered in Pittsburgh, February 8, 1919; and letters between Carter Glass and Robert F. Wagner concerning proposed amendment to the Federal Reserve Act in 1938.
- Political Correspondence 1930-1940 (Box 274)
  A. Folder of letters relating to the University of Virginia dispute; About a dozen letters from bankers on various aspects of proposed monetary and banking legislation; Correspondence between Carter Glass and Rixey Smith on Bishop James Cannon and miscellaneous matters; Folder of letters on Bacon-Shakespeare controversy, including copy of an interview with William Smedley; Speeches and memoranda relating to taxes.
- Personal Correspondence 1931-1934 (Box 275)
  A. Miscellaneous personal correspondence: About 300 letters including those of Colgate W. Darden, Eugene Black, Bernard M. Baruch, W. P. Wood, Jouett Shouse, and Mrs. Woodrow Wilson; Letters of commendation on his 1933 speech regarding the New Deal.
- Invitations 1930-1933 (Box 276)
  A. Invitations received from 1930-1933; Letters of acceptance or regrets.
- Correspondence: Bishop James Cannon Case 1931 (Box 277)
  A. Several hundred photostated pages of memoranda for the Attorney General from J. Edgar Hoover on the subject of bribery in the Goldhurst case; Other photostated documents, including the statements of Joseph Radlow and Miss Failor.
- Correspondence: Federal Reserve 1931 (Box 278)
  A. Folder of correspondence marked, "Federal Reserve Act Changes No. I" containing letters which express the writer's attitude toward broadening the definition of eligible paper, forming a National Credit Corporation, extending branch and chain banking and examining banks more carefully, including letters of: Eugene Meyer, Angus McLean, George Harrison, Charles S. Hamlin, F. W. Taussig, J. H. Case, Robert J. Bulkley, Bernard M. Baruch, and Alfred L. Aikin. ca. 400 letter; A folder containing about 450 letters primarily on the above mentioned subjects. Correspondents include: H. Parker Willis, Richard C. Whitney, Arthur H. Vandenburg, Joseph T. Robinson, Samuel D. Pettengell and Peter Norbeck.
- Correspondence 1931 (Box 279)
  A. Ca. 300 letters of various political and legislative matters: Letter from Newton D. Baker containing suggestions for the Democratic Platform in 1932; Correspondence with S. O. Bland relating to the payment of "prevailing wages" on Federal projects in Virginia; Letter from Carter Glass to R. B. Cassel expressing his views on the poor administration of the Federal Reserve Act; Correspondence between Carter Glass and William G. McAdoo; Letter, April 3, 1931, from William G. McAdoo denying that the so-called Treasury Plan was suggested by either Samuel Untermeyer or Robert L. Owen.
- Correspondence 1931-1932 (Box 280)
  A. Ca. 400 letters covering miscellaneous political and personal matters: Correspondence with Bernard M. Baruch regarding the political situation in 1931; Correspondence with E. C. Branson enclosing a statement from Charles S. Hamlin in the subject "The Right of Federal Reserve banks to Produce Foreign Bonds and Use Them as Security for Federal Reserve Notes;" Letters of Harry F. Byrd pertaining to political support of various leaders in Virginia; Letter from Carter Glass to Horace N. Hawkins concerning Wilson's attitude toward a third term and his actions at the 1920 convention; Correspondence with Governor John G. Pollard relating to the appointment of a United States Marshall in the eastern District of Virginia and to other political matters in Virginia.
- Correspondence: Banking and Currency 1921-1933 (Box 281)
  A. Papers relating to the preparation of the McFadden Bill, including a long letter from H. Parker Willis to Senator King, February 5, 1927, and a memorandum prepared for Senator Carter Glass by Charles W. Collins; Letter from Charles S. Hamlin enclosing what appears to be suggested changes in Carter Glass' Chronicle; Statement "Some Notable Achievements of the Federal Reserve System, " unsigned and undated; Memorandum in Carter Glass' handwriting of conversation and communications with Charles S. Hamlin, Paul M. Warburg and W. P. G. Harding concerning the plan of the Federal Reserve Board to reduce the number of Reserve Banks; Folder marked, "Treasury -Letters of Congratulation." Ca. 200, dated, 1933; Carter Glass' handwritten opinion of par check clearance; Typewritten memoranda with marginal notations in Carter Glass' handwriting concerning the action of the Federal Reserve Board in 1920; Memorandum prepared by Walter Wyatt, "Brief Statement of Present Legal Status of Par Clearance System." November 26, 1926; Memorandum on the Carter Glass - Robert L. Owen Banking Bill; Letter from Edmund Platt, January 9, 1922, reviewing the controversy over Reserve policies in which J. S. Williams and others were then engaged; Letter from John Skelton Williams to Carter Glass, June 21, 1921, explaining his position; Correspondence pertaining to the Federal Reserve, including letters of George Seay, W. P. G. Harding and John Skelton Williams.
- Correspondence: Legislation 1932 (Box 282)
  A. Folder of ca. 25 letters concerning the Bus Bill; Folder of Correspondence concerning the Children's Bureau; Folder of ca. 400 letters concerning Vocational Education.
- Correspondence regarding Banking and Currency, Federal Reserve 1913-1932 (Box 283)
  A. Folder of correspondence with Russell C. Leffingwell, 1920-1932. In addition to letters of a personal nature there are many which deal with monetary and financial matters; Letters, April 25, 1932 and February 20, 1932, suggest the importance of Leffingwell's ideas in the formulation of the Carter Glass Bill. In letters dated April 29, 1932 and April 5, 1932 the Federal Reserve and Treasury policies of 1919- 1920 and the behavior of Charles Mitchell in 1929 are discussed; Number of memoranda, 1919, giving information regarding the financial situation in that year. Letter of February 25, 1924, discusses the participation of Eugene Meyer in the revival of the War Finance Corporation; Letters, February 3, 1923, and February 6, 1923, record the views of both Leffingwell and Carter Glass on the subject of the payment of foreign debts by our Allies.
  B. About 10 loose papers, including a memoranda which gives the opinions of the following Senators on various provisions of the Federal Reserve Act at the time of the House- Senate Conference: Bristow, Reed, Wilson, Thomas Ashurst, Lavis Shaffroth, Weeks and Hayes; Record of voting in the House- Senate Conference.